Finding Aid for Tom Van Zoeren oral history collection, 1860s-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Tom Van Zoeren oral history collection 1860s-2011 2000-2010
Van Zoeren, Tom
0129 Aa 2
Tom Van Zoeren was a park ranger at Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore. His collection contains oral history interviews relating to the history of the Sleeping Bear Dunes region and other Michigan localities.
1.5 linear feet
58.2 GB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Tom Van Zoeren (donor no. 9079 ) in several accessions beginning in 2001.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Tom Van Zoeren worked as a park ranger at Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore from 1984 to 2005. He conducted oral history interviews with many older residents of the park area.
The Van Zoeren collection contains numerous oral history interviews conducted between 1979 and 2010, and also includes copies of scanned photos and other supporting documents. The interviews are available variously on audio cassette tapes, audio compact discs, video DVDs, and online. Transcripts or summaries are found in the collection for many of the interviews. The Van Zoeren collection is organized in two sections by format.
The first section contains analog files and physical media such as CDs and DVDs. This section is arranged in the following series by family interview: Basch/Lanham/Van Zoeren oral history interviews, 1993-2000; George Burfiend oral history interviews, photo collection, and farm tour, 2005-2008; DeKorne family oral history and photographs, 2006; Doan family oral history interview, 2006; Dottie (Ashmore) Lanham oral history and photograph collection, 2003-2008; Alfred and Loraine (Olsen) Mason oral history interview and photo collection, 2001-2004; Leonard Thoreson oral history interview and photos, 2005-2006; and Frederick and Margretha Werner Farm oral history interview and photo collection, 2006-2007. These series contain information related to the families and interviews in the form of text, scanned and printed images, and audio and video recordings.
Information about selected specific interviews:
Basch, Laura (Oleson), of the Port Oneida, Mich., area (audio cassettes and online)
Burfiend, George, relating to Burfiend farm and Port Oneida (compact discs, video DVDs, and online)
DeKorne, Jack relating to the family of Boudewyn and Kate DeKorne of Grand Rapids and Glen Lake, Mich. (compact disc and online)
Fargo, Judy Carole and Ruth Ann Doan Jones, relating to the Frank and Alma Doan family of Croswell, Mich. (compact discs and online, filed under Doan family)
Lanham, Dottie, relating to her life and to Burdickville and surrounding area (compact discs and online)
Lanham, John, of Burdickville, Mich. (audio cassettes and online)
Mason, Alfred and Lorraine [referred to as 'Loraine' in some collection materials] (Olsen), relating to their families, the family farms and the Port Oneida community (compact discs and online)
Miller, Charles, relating to the Frederick and Margretha Werner farm in Port Oneida (compact discs, video DVD, and online, filed under Werner)
Stuber, Mary Lou, relating to the Frederick and Margretha Werner farm in Port Oneida. (compact discs and online, filed under Werner)
Thoresen, Leonard, relating to his family, the family farm and the Port Oneida community (compact discs, video DVD, and online)
Thoreson, Leonard, relating to the Frederick and Margretha Werner farm in Port Oneida (video DVD and online, filed under Werner)
Van Noord, Trudy, relating to the family of Boudewyn and Kate DeKorne of Grand Rapids and Glen Lake, Mich. (compact disc and online, filed under DeKorne family)
Van Zoeren, Jay, of Vriesland, Mich., 1948 graduate of the University of Michigan Medical School (audio cassettes and online)
Additional files relating to these and other persons were received on a hard drive and are available online.
The second section consists of one series of digitized material, Oral histories, photos, and other historic materials from the Sleeping Bear Dunes region. The digital files were created or assembled by Van Zoeren and were received on an external hard drive. This series is further divided into subseries by type of material: Information on Farms, Families, etc.; Oral History Audio Files; Historic Images; Video Recordings; Genealogies; Census and Cemetery Records; Historic Maps; and Other Resources. Some of the content may be digitized versions of items in the analog portion of the collection.
Subjects:
Burdickville (Mich.)--History.; Croswell (Mich.); DeKorne family.; DeKorne Furniture Company.; Doan family.; Dutch Americans--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Dutch Americans--Michigan--Vriesland.; Farm life--Michigan--Croswell.; Farm life--Michigan--Leelanau County.; Farm life--Michigan--Vriesland.; German Americans--Michigan--Croswell.; Glen Lake (Leelanau County, Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Lanham family.; Leelanau County (Mich.); Norwegian Americans--Michigan--Leelanau County.; Olson family.; Thoresen family.; University of Michigan. Medical School--Students.; Van Zoeren family.; Werner, Frederick.; Werner, Margretha.; Vriesland (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Leelanau County.; Port Oneida (Mich.)
Contributors:
Basch, Laura E., 1911-; Burfiend, George.; Fargo, Judy Carole.; Jones, Ruth Ann Doan.; Lanham, Dottie.; Lanham, John, 1927-; Mason, Alfred.; Mason, Loraine Olsen, 1922-; Thoreson, Leonard.; Van Zoeren, Jay.
Genre Terms:
Compact discs.; Digital audio formats.; Digital images.; Digital moving image formats.; Genealogies (histories); Oral histories.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Basch / Lanham / Van Zoeren oral history interviews 1993-2000, audio cassettes
  - Laura Basch 1993, 9 audiocassettes with summaries (Box 1)
  - John Lanham 2000, 3 audiocassettes with summaries (Box 1)
  - Jay Van Zoeren interviews 1995-1996, 7 audiocassettes (Box 1)
- George Burfiend oral history interviews, photo collection, and farm tour 2005-2008
  - "Images and Recollections from Port Oneida: The Burfiend and Baker Farms," booklet of captioned photos (Box 2)
  - Tour of the Burfiend farm with George Burfiend 2005, 3 optical disks DVDs with summary (Box 2)
  - George Burfiend interviews 2006-2007, 5 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Image and text files, 1 optical disks CD (Box 2)
- DeKorne family oral history and photographs 2006
  - "Boudewijn & Kate DeKorne: A Short Oral and Photographic Family History" 3rd ed. 2009 and 4th ed. 2011 (Box 2)
  - Jack DeKorne interview, 6 optical disks audio CDs with outline (Box 2)
  - Trudy Van Noord interview, 1 optical disks audio CD with outline (Box 2)
  - Printouts of scanned photos and other images (Box 2)
  - Images and text files, 1 optical disks CD (Box 2)
- Doan family oral history interview 2006
  - Judy Carole Fargo and Ruth Ann Doan Jones interview, 2 optical disks audio CDs with summary (Box 2)
  - Printouts of scanned photos (Box 2)
  - Image and text files, 1 optical disks CD (Box 2)
- Dottie (Ashmore) Lanham oral history and photograph collection 2003-2008
  - "Dottie Lanham of Burdickville: Images, Recollections, and Observations," booklet of captioned photos (Box 2)
  - Printouts of scanned photos (Box 2)
  - Interview 2003, 2 optical disks audio CDs with transcript (Box 2)
  - Interviews 2005-2008, 4 optical disks audio CDs with summary (Box 2)
  - Image and text files, 1 optical disks CD (Box 2)
- Alfred and Loraine (Olsen) Mason oral history interview and photo collection 2001-2004
  - Alfred and Loraine [Lorraine?] Mason interview regarding the Charles and Hattie Olsen farm, Port Oneida, and surrounding areas, 4 optical disks audio CDs with summary (Box 2)
  - Printouts of scanned photos (Box 2)
  - Image and text files, 1 optical disks CD (Box 2)
- Leonard Thoreson oral history interview and photos 2005-2006
  - "Images & Recollections from Port Oneida: The Thoreson Farm and its Neighbors," booklet of text, photos, and CD-ROM of oral history excerpts (Box 2)
  - Leonard Thoreson interview, 7 optical disks audio CDs with summary (Box 2)
  - Farm tour, 1 optical disks video DVD with summary (Box 2)
  - Printouts of scanned photos with captions (Box 2)
- Frederick and Margretha Werner Farm oral history interview and photo collection 2006-2007, 1 optical disks CD
  - "Images and Recollections from Port Oneida: The Frederick and Margretha Werner Farm," booklet of captioned photos (Box 2)
  - Charles Miller interview 2006 with summary (Box 2)
  - Mary Lou Stuber interview 2006 with summary (Box 2)
  - Farm and barn tour with Charles Miller and Leonard Thoreson undated (Box 2)
  - Scanned photographs and other images (Box 2)
- Oral histories, photos, and other historic materials from the Sleeping Bear Dunes region, digital files, originally on 1 hard drive, USB connection
  - Information on Farms, Families, etc. 1933-2010
    The Information on Farms, Families, etc. subseries (71.3 MB, 1933-2010) contains oral history interview summaries and transcripts as well as correspondence, histories in written forms, and compilations of references to particular farms found in other interviews or documents. Files are arranged geographically by region and area, and then by family or farm.
    - Sleeping Bear Dunes Region 1933-2010
      - Burdickville Area, 1933-circa 2010, .ZIP file
        - DeKorne Family
          - DeKorne, Jack interview (summary) 2006
          - Ryskamp, Ken interview (summary) 2007
          - Van Noord, Trudy interview (summary) 2006
        - Dewing, Preston autobiography 1933, 1998
        - Gilbert, Lurah Dewing autobiography 1997
        - Holden Family
          - Holden, David interview (summary) 1976
          - Holden, Mary Ellen and Margaret interview (summary) undated
          - Johnson, Sarah and David Holden interview (summary) undated
        - Lanham, Dottie interviews (transcript and summary) 2003, 2005-2008
        - Lanham, Nancy
          - Interview (transcript and summary) 2009
          - "My Life" autobiography undated
        - Individual files
          - Ashmore, John interview (summary) 2009
          - Crosby, John interview (summary) 2009
          - Faulman interview (transcript) 2004
          - Hansen, Clarissa interview (summary) 1994
          - Johnson, Oscar autobiography 1942, undated
          - Lanham, Dorothy E interview (transcript) 2003
          - Trumbull, Nolan interview (summary) 2008
          - Wepking, Jeannette interview (summary) 2009
          - Whitten, Gene interview (transcript) 2008-2009
          - Whitten, Gene obituary circa 2010
      - Other Areas 2000-2010, .ZIP file
        - John Lanham interview (transcript and summary) 2000
        - Bufka Farm interviews (brief summaries) 2004
        - Musil, Bessie interview (transcript and summary) 2008
        - South Manitou correspondence 2009-2010
        - Individual files
          - Cate, Lowell of Cedar interview (summary) 2010
          - John Westman correspondence 2010
          - Martha Evelyn Cleaver correspondence undated
          - Roe, Honora of Maple City interview (summary) 2009
      - Port Oneida Area 1979, 1992-2010, .ZIP file
        - Anderson Farm, note of references
        - Baker Farm
          - Baker, Fred interview (summary) 1979
          - Barratt, Jack and Lucille interviews (summaries) 1992, 2003, 2004-2007, 2008
          - Barratt, Bill interview (transcript) 2003
          - Oleson, Ruth interviews (summary) 2003, 2004
        - Basch, Martin Farm, note of references
        - Basch, Niclous Farm
          - Arlene Moody interview (transcript and summary) 2009
          - Laura Basch interviews (transcripts and index) 1993-1995
          - Vulcanizer information, circa 2010
        - Behrens Farm, note of references
        - Burfiend, Carsten Farm
          - David Ritter discussion (summary) 2005
          - George Burfiend interviews (summaries) 2005-2007
          - Howard L Burfiend correspondence 2009-2010
          - Mary Brayton notes 2007
          - Miscellaneous notes
        - Burfiend, John Farm
          - Betty and June Garthe interview (notes) 2003
          - Ed Schmidt interview (transcript and summary) 2008
          - Schmidt family members interview (summary) 2010
        - Burfiend, Peter Farm, note of references
        - Dechow Farm
          - Dechow-Shalda family members interview (transcript and summary) 2009
          - Jill Baxter interview (transcript) 2007
          - Robert Klett tour/interview (transcript and summary) 2008
        - Eckerdt, George Farm, note of references
        - Eckerdt, Henry Farm
          - Beverly Yvonne Krcek interview (transcript and summary) 2008
          - Farm tours/interviews (summaries) 2008, 2010
        - Kelderhouse, Thomas Farm
          - Kay Bond interview (summary) 2010
          - Charlotte Groesser interview (transcript) 2009
          - Myrtle Kelderhouse Warner story 2008
          - Nancy and Margaret Hulka discussion (summary) 2007
          - Note of references
        - Kelderhouse, William Farm
          - Leon Kelderhouse interview (summary) 2006
          - Ruth Lambkin interview (summary) 2008
        - Kirkett Farm, note of references
        - Lawr Farm, note of references
        - Miller, Carsten Farm, note of references
        - Miller, Fred Farm
          - Jerry and Gerry Miller correspondence 2009
          - Patricia Ann Cartensen interview (summary) 2009
          - Paula Jones notes 2009
          - Robert Adair interview (summary) 2009
          - Ellen Miller recipes undated
        - Millington Farm, note of references
        - Olsen, Charles Farm
          - Alfred and Lorraine Mason interviews (transcript and summaries) 2001-2004
          - Olsen family reunion interviews (summaries) 2007
          - Garnett Olsen conversation (notes) 2007
          - Jerry Mack correspondence 2009
        - Olsen, Everett Farm, note of references
        - Olsen, George Farm
          - Farm information undated
          - Walter Houdek notes undated
        - Olsen, Ole Farm information and note of references
        - Port Oneida School
          - Lucille Baker Barratt and Lorraine Shelby Richardson interview (summary) 2001
          - Note of references
        - Schmidt Farm, note of references
        - Thoreson Farm
          - Leonard Thoreson interviews (transcript and summary) 2006
          - Poem and note of references undated
        - Warner Farm
          - Gene Warner recollections 2009
          - Note of references
        - Watkins Cottage
          - Article 2005
          - Judith C. Watkins, Katharine Wylde, and Mary Crane interview (summary) 2005
          - Mary Crane correspondence 2006-2010
        - Weaver Farm, note of references
        - Werner, Frederick Farm
          - Charles H. Miller interview (summary) 2006
          - Charles Miller and Leonard Thoreson barn tour/interview (transcript) 2008
          - James Vachow, "Epilogue -- 1857" undated
          - Kathryn Keller notes undated
          - Mary Lou Stuber interview (summary) 2007
          - Siblings Charles H. Miller, Rose Mary Frederick, and Mary Lou Stuber interview (summary) 2009
          - Johnny Warner and Gene Warner notes 2008
          - Robert Hangerman genealogy notes/correspondence 2009
        - Werner, Richard Farm
          - Gene Warner correspondence 2009
          - Note of references
    - Other Areas 1995-1996, 2003-2009, .ZIP file
      - Scott Family
        - Alice Elizabeth Bahls interview (summary) 2007
        - Dorothy Scott Patton interview (summary) 2006
        - Peggy Scott McCreight interview (summary) 2006
        - Miscellaneous documents and notes undated
      - Van Zoeren Family
        - Carolyn Van Zoeren interview (summary) 2009
        - Jay Van Zoeren interview (summary) 1995-1996
        - Jay Van Zoeren obituary 2005
        - Reflections on My Dad by Tom Van Zoeren, circa 2010
      - Doan family (Judy Carole Fargo and Ruth Ann Doan Jones) interview (summary) 2006
    - Port Oneida Fair Oral History Project interview (partial transcript and summary) 2010, .ZIP file
  - Oral History Audio Files 1976-2010
    The Oral History Audio Files subseries (35.0 GB, 1976-2010) consists of audio files for oral history interviews, primarily conducted by Tom Van Zoeren. Recordings are arranged geographically by region and area, and then by family or farm. Audio files may be in several formats (original session recordings of the interview or series of interviews, a version divided into tracks, or versions converted to different file formats) and may have been digitized from analog media or born digital.
    - Sleeping Bear Dunes Region 1976-2010
      - Burdickville Area 1976-2010
        - Ashmore, John interview 2010, .ZIP file
        - Cotner, Leonard interview 2008, .ZIP file
        - Crosby, John interview 2009, .ZIP file
        - DeKorne Family 2006-2007, .ZIP files
          - DeKorne, Jack series of interviews 2006
          - Ryskamp, Ken interview 2007
          - Van Noord, Trudy interview 2006
        - Faulman, Ellsworth and Lucille interview 2004, .ZIP file
        - Hansen, Clarissa interview 1994, .ZIP file
        - Holden Family interviews 1976-1992, .ZIP file
        - Lanham interviews 2003-2009, .ZIP files
          - Lanham, Dottie series of interviews 2005-2008
          - Lanham, Dottie interview 2003
          - Lanham, Nancy interview 2009
        - Trumbull, Nolan interview 2008, .ZIP file
        - Wepking, Jeannette interview 2009, .ZIP file
        - Whitten, Gene interviews 2008-2009, .ZIP file
      - Other Areas 2000-2009
        - Bufka Farm 2004, .ZIP file
          - Group discussion 2004
          - Bufka, Jerome and John interview 2004
          - Bufka, Jerome tour/interview 2004
        - Cate, Lowell Chamberlain interview 2010, .ZIP file
        - Lanham, John interview 2000, .ZIP file
        - Musil, Bessie Jane Plowman interview 2008, .ZIP file
        - Roe, Honora of Maple City / Barbara Louise Liljestrand, Maxine Louise Wepking Mikowski, and Helen Louise Mikowski interview 2009, .ZIP files
      - Port Oneida Area 1979-2010
        - Baker Farm 1979, 2004-2008, .ZIP files
          - Baker, Fred, interview 1979
          - Barratt, Jack and Lucille, series of interviews 2004-2007
          - Barratt, Jack interview 2008
          - Oleson, Ruth interview 2004
        - Basch, Niclous, Farm 1993-1995, 2009, .ZIP files
          - Basch, Laura, series of interviews 1993-1995
          - Moody, Arlene, interview 2009
        - Burfiend, Carsten Farm 2005-2007, .ZIP file and .WAV file
          - Burfiend, George, series of interviews 2006-2007
          - Ritter, David, conversation 2005
        - Burfiend, John, Farm 2008-2010, .ZIP files
          - Schmidt, Ed, interviews 2008
          - Schmidt Family Reunion interview 2010
        - Dechow Farm 2007-2009, .MP3 file and .ZIP files
          - Baxter, Jil,l interview 2007
          - Dechow-Shalda reunion interview 2009
          - Klett, Rober,t interview 2008
        - Eckerdt, Henry, Farm 2008-2010, .ZIP files
          - Krcek, Beverly Yvonne interview 2008
          - Eckerdt Farm Tour 1 2008
          - Eckerdt Farm Tour 2 2008
          - Eckerdt Farm Tour 3 2010
        - Kelderhouse, Thomas Farm 2007-2010, .ZIP files
          - Bond, Kay interview 2010
          - Groesser, Charlotte interview 2009
          - Hulka, Nancy and Margaret interview 2007
        - Kelderhouse, William Farm 2006-2008, .ZIP files
          - Kelderhouse, Leon interviews 2006
          - Lambkin, Ruth interview 2008
        - Miller, Fred Farm 2009, .ZIP files
          - Adair, Robert (Bob) interview 2009
          - Carstensen, Pat (Patricia Ann Miller) interview 2009
        - Olsen, Charles Farm 2001-2007, .ZIP files
          - Mason, Alfred and Lorraine series of interviews 2001-2004
          - Olsen Family reunion interviews 2007
        - Thoreson Farm 2005-2010, .ZIP files
          - Thoreson, Leonard first series of interviews 2005-2006
          - Thoreson, Leonard second series of interviews 2009-2010
        - Watkins Cottage, Judith C. Watkins, Katharine Watkins Wylde, and Mary Watkins Crane interview 2005, .ZIP file
        - Werner Frederick Farm 2006-2009, .ZIP files
          - Miller, Charles H. and Leonard Thoreson Barn Tour interview 2008
          - Miller, Charles interviews 2006
          - Miller siblings (Charles, Mary Rose, and Mary Lou) interview 2009
          - Stuber, Mary Lou interview 2007
    - Other Areas 1995-2009
      - Doan Family interview (Judy Carole Fargo and Ruth Ann Doan Jones) 2006, .ZIP file
      - Gallup, Albert interview 2005, .ZIP file
      - Scott Family 2006-2007, .ZIP files
        - Bahls, Alice Elizabeth interview 2007
        - McCreight, Peggy Scott interview 2006
        - Patton, Dorothy Scott interview 2006
      - Van Zoeren Family 1995-1996, 2009, .ZIP files
        - Van Zoeren, Carolyn interview 2009
        - Van Zoeren, Jay interviews 1995-1996
    - Port Oneida Fair Oral History Project interviews 2010, .ZIP file
  - Historic Images 1860s-2010s
    The Historic Images subseries (7.7 GB, 1860s-2010s) includes images of photographs and postcards as well as documents such as newspaper clippings and marriage or baptismal certificates. Photographs and postcards depict individuals and groups, structures, animals, the land, and other subjects such as ships and trains related to the history of the region and its inhabitants. The original items date from the mid-nineteenth century through the early twenty-first with the bulk dating from the first half of the twentieth century. Images are arranged geographically by region and area, and then by family, farm, or subject. In some cases both original and edited versions of images are included.
    - Sleeping Bear Dunes Region 1860s-2010s
      - Burdickville Area, 1877-circa 2010, .ZIP files
        - Addington, Conley Collection
        - Burdickville Meteor
        - Burdickville Miscellaneous, including 'Top of the World'
        - DeKorne Family Collections
          - Byl Photo Collection
          - Casey DK Photo Collection
            - Case & Bess Family
            - Kik Family
            - Van Zoeren Family
          - Jack DeKorne Photo Collection
          - Ryskamp Family Photo Collection
          - Wierenga Collection
        - Dickinson Collection
        - Faulman Collection
        - Helm, Nan Collection
          - General images
          - Nan's home
        - Lanham, Dottie Collection
        - Lanham, John Images
        - Lanham, Nancy Collection
        - Maple City Mirror
        - Van Zoeren Family Collection
          - DeKorne Side of Family
          - Van Zoeren Side of Family
      - Empire circa 1910, .ZIP file
        - General images
        - Lucille Barratt Collection
      - Glen Haven Area, circa 1926, .ZIP file
      - Glen Lake Area, circa 1930, .ZIP file
      - National Park Service (NPS) File Photos, circa 1970s-1980s, 1989, .ZIP file
      - North Manitou Island, Musil collection, circa 1915, .ZIP file
      - Port Oneida 1860s-2010s, .ZIP files
        - Baker Farm
          - General images
          - Family Bible Pages
          - Lucille Barratt Collection
          - Ruth Oleson Collection
          - Taro Barratt related Photos
          - Tom Van Zoeren Baker_Barratt Photos
        - Basch, Martin Farm, Jerry Basch Collection
        - Basch, Niclous Farm
          - Alice Van Zoeren Nic Basch Farm
          - Grace Dickinson N Basch Farm
          - Laura Basch Collection
          - Laura Basch Documents Collection
          - Tom Van Zoeren Nic Basch Farm Photos
        - Brunson Farm
        - Burfiend, Carsten Farm
          - General images
          - Burfiend Family Collection
          - George Burfiend Collection
          - Howard Lee Burfiend Collection
          - Jack Barratt Collection